the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to perform Hello friends
I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a professor of
Kinesiology in the center for sport
performance at Cal State Fullerton in
today's episode we're going to be
talking about specifically how to
improve your V2 Max in previous episodes
we talked about the heart we went over
what it is how it works why you should
care about it we also spent some time
going over the three eyes so how to
investigate or ESS your overall
cardiovascular function how to interpret
that to know whether it's good bad
terrible or potentially a world record
then how to intervene so what to do
about it and how to improve its function
if you missed that previous episode we
did on the heart please go back and
check that out but I'd be remissed to
not remind you or tell you for the first
time about how important V2 Max is if
you want all the studies direct links
specific details on the statistics and
values you can see that in the previous
episode as well as the show notes for
that episode but really quickly your V2
Max is one of the most significant
predictors of all cause mortality that
we know of in fact if you compare it to
more traditional markers like blood
pressure smoking history cholesterol
levels while those are all very
important V2 Max can be two to three to
even up to fourfold higher predictor of
survival and mortality than those other
traditional markers so it's insanely
important and in fact many folks would
argue it is the most most important
metric to pay attention to if you want
to know how long you're going to live
now I apologize for being overly
dramatic about that but really it is
that astounding about how important that
number is to determining how long you're
going to live the other important point
about this is there is no upper limit
such that the higher your V2 Max the
higher your chance of survival continues
to go it really doesn't seem to get to
any point of diminishing returns and so
it's a metric that is within your
control it is arguably
one of if not the most important metric
for how long you're going to live and
the higher the better and so focusing on
this whether you want to run a marathon
or want to play sports it really doesn't
matter if you want to live longer and
better V2 Max should be one of your top
priorities but in today's discussion I
wanted to do something a little bit
different and that is really spend our
entire time going over practical
applications I want to walk you through
exact programs and protocols
uh giving you both the concepts as well
as specific methodologies as samples to
help you get guided in either developing
your own program or helping others with
theirs in order to do that I need to
start with a very quick overview of what
we're trying to actually accomplish when
we're improving our endurance or V2 Max
so that you understand the different
components that tend to be pretty
similar amongst all different styles and
training approaches I promise we'll keep
that very brief after that we're going
to jump right into a very specific
protocol for improving your V2 Max and
then after that I'm going to share with
you a specific protocol a friend of mine
used to complete his first ever Marathon
now before we go too much further I'd
like to take a quick break and thank our
sponsors because they make this show
possible not only are they on this list
because they offer great products and
services but because I actually
personally love them and use them myself
today's episode is brought to you by
element element is an electrolite drink
mix that has an ideal ratio of sodium
potassium and magnesium but has no sugar
elect ites are critical to proper
hydration which I've been harping on for
years but you can't do that by only
drinking water in fact many of you will
probably remember that I featured
element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration all the way back in
2020 which is obviously long before this
podcast even existed so I've been a fan
of element for a long time in fact as
student listeners will also realize
these hydration videos were the Genesis
of the Galpin hydration equation named
not by me but by by the legendary
neuroscientist Dr Andrew hubman I
featured element in these videos because
they're blend of 1,000 mg of sodium 200
migs potassium and 60 milligrams
magnesium really is different than any
other electrolyte on the market and has
great scientific support however I want
to be ultra clear 1,000 milligram of
sodium is a lot and not everyone needs
that much in fact that may be way too
much if you don't exercise or sweat much
already eat a lot of salt in your diet
say from a lot of processed foods or
otherwise have sodium related medical
concerns I personally use the Citrus and
watermelon flavors a ton to preh hydrate
before heading out on a full day of
training or long hike or a hunt since I
know I'll be losing a bunch of fluids
and won't have many opportunities to
take things with me element has also
just released a new line of canned
sparkling element which I am all about
if you'd like to try element you can go
to drink LM nt.com perform to claim a
free element sample pack with a purchase
of any element drink mix again that's
drink LM nt.com perform to claim a free
sample pack today's episode is also
brought to you by Vitality blueprint
Vitality is the world's only
comprehensive blood work company built
specifically for high performance as
we'll cover throughout the season of the
perform podcast a highquality blood test
is one of the best ways to better
understand your physiology and areas for
improvement Vitality blueprint uses over
100 molecular biomarkers that are
critical to physical and mental
performance then provides unrivaled
interpretation and Analysis of these
data so you know exactly what's going on
in your body from there vitality's
Innovative software allows you to easily
create clear and highly specific
lifestyle nutrition and supplementation
plans based upon your unique physiology
and goals experience the world's most
premium performance blood work by going
to Vitality blueprint.com
perform I know exactly how dope this
thing is because Dan Garner and I built
it ourselves based upon that system
we've used in thousands of athletes over
the last decade or so so we're stoked
that something that's previously only
been accessible to the world's most
decorated athletes musicians and so on
is now open to everyone let's finally
get you looking feeling and performing
at your absolute best and that starts by
going to Vitality blueprint.com
perform let's go so to get us started I
really do think it's important that we
zoom out just a little bit when we say
improve our V2 Max we have to
acknowledge that that is only one
component of endurance so do you truly
mean V2 Max or do you mean your ability
to have more energy throughout the day
to feel less fatigued those are really
different conversations all important
but in this particular example I want to
focus on really improving just the V2
Max okay so then thinking through that I
like to use a method called first
principles which says let's Zoom all the
way out let's think about everything
that would have to happen for me to have
a high VO2 max and then number one
analyze my own self to figure out where
in that program am I fatiguing or
lacking and then how do I solve it all
right if you don't know then you would
actually just do a program that
addresses all potential areas of failure
if you do know your area of failure then
you would probably hedge a little bit
more towards that what do I mean well we
could come up with any number of
examples here but let's say you are
feeling like you're just not running as
fast fast as you used to well that may
not be a view to Max issue it may be a
speed issue maybe a mechanics issue
let's say you're having a different
issue where you're feeling fatigued in
games if you're an athlete well this may
actually have to do with your warm-up it
could be nutrition related it could be
sports psychology you are upregulated or
down regulated or something like that
and so when we really go into solving
problems for high performers I would
encourage you to not just grab a program
like this put it in place and assume
it's going to work for everyone it may
work for many obviously I'm going to
present to you programs I think are very
effective but I really would encourage
you to think through the performance of
you and your individual
situation uh in my experience it's not
always a physiological issue there could
be other lower hanging fruit that
improves your performance in a way that
you care about that's not necessarily
just physiology all that aside let's go
ahead and dive into V2 Max remember what
we're talking about here is a central
and peripheral issue meaning Central as
in your cardiovascular system
specifically really your heart and
peripheral as in your musculature so
there's two sides of this equation V2
Max the equation I like to use the
modified fi equation which we talked
about and described in the previous
cardiac episode is your V2 Max is
equivalent to your heart rate multiplied
by your stroke volume that's also heart
rate times stroke volume is known as
your cardiac output multiplied by your
av2 difference and so it's how much
blood you can get out of your heart per
pump how how many pumps you can get away
with that's the Q that's the cardiac
output multiplied by your avo2
difference which tells you how much
oxygen you can extract from your blood
into your working tissue all right so
I'm going to stop right there with the
details that's really what we have to
think about and so how long the way then
we start thinking all right where is my
point of failure if I'm limited in my
stroke volume why is it because my
heart's too small okay well solving that
problem is a different style of training
than if my issue is extracting oxygen
into tissue there's a different training
solution for that maybe your issue is
mechanics of your lungs so maybe you're
not breathing properly or maybe your
intercostals or diaphragm fatigue maybe
it's posture related and so there's
various components we want to get into
to really addresses so high endurance
athlete or endurance performance
solutions are individuals who can dive
into that stuff and figure out hey your
most your biggest hole here your biggest
problem is this particular area and so
we're going to design your protocols to
solve that problem right nonetheless
though let's assume you don't have any
of that information and we'll just move
through with one quality example I will
reiterate just one more time there are
many many many ways to improve V2 Max
I've talked to and know a bunch of high
level endurance coaches there's a ton of
research in this as well and so you
could pull up just endless amounts of
protocols my goal is to not tell you
that the protocol I'm about to present
to you is the best or better than
anything else but it is just a sample of
one protocol that I know works very well
and so depending on your goals and
situation you may want to make many
changes or use an entirely different
setup all those caveats is say now let's
finally jump into the protocol remember
when we say V2 I'm assuming you mean V2
Max which is that maximal capacity or
ability maximum heart rate maximum
oxygen extraction maximum stroke volume
Etc you may actually be more interested
in something like a submaximal
performance perance so how can I cover
more distance at a given heart rate or
how can I run my race faster or how can
I perform better without getting so
tired in my given event in my pickle
ball or canoeing or volleyball or
whatever I'm playing those are different
conversations we're really going to talk
about how to maximize the V2 right now
we'll cover the things like performing
better in your Marathon a little bit
later all right so V2 Max training then
per se says all right we've got three
major components to discuss the very
first one is What is your modality in
other words what's your exercise if you
are exercise agnostic then you really
you can pick anything you want you can
push a sled you can Sprint you can uh
swim you can bike you can use an assault
bike you can use whatever you would like
if you're trying to improve performance
and again a given race or your V2 Max
for a fight or a competition then you're
going to want to pick the mode specific
to that okay again if you are simply
after the V2 Max then you are mode agnos
in fact you could probably use a
combination and probably should use a
combination of different modalities what
you want to do is pick something that
accomplishes two things one allows you
to execute sufficient effort so you can
do this a bunch at a high effort high
intensity or long duration or high focus
or whatever we're going to want to do
there and then secondly one that's not
limiting your technical proficiency so
if you're not good at running I wouldn't
recommend doing this one of the common
and largest mistakes folks make when
trying to improve their V to Max or in
general is they hop into things like
running and then they just start adding
volume so they do one mile today and two
miles the next week and three Etc or
intensity so they do you know 30 seconds
of hard work and then they do three
rounds of that and then next week they
do four rounds then five rounds and we
start building this intensity and volume
on top of either truly dysfunctional or
suboptimal movement patterns and that
results in a lot of injury and a lot of
excessive fatigue okay so you want to be
really careful pick something you are
technically proficient in if you are
modality agnostic and something you're
not going to be um broken down or
injured with the next thing then is the
intensity and the volume we're going to
want to play with every coach defines
these things differently uh they think
you should spend a different amount of
time in different zones you can kind of
think of this though almost all coaches
acknowledge there's at least three
potentially four areas that you should
train in the bottom easiest level if you
like to call this Zone one or zone two
you can I don't honestly candidly don't
use that stuff much um You can call
these gear one or Gear 2 if you're Brian
McKenzie or someone like that you could
call these things just more like Blue
Zone um you could call them RP or
relative perceived exertion how hard
does this feel on a scale of 1 to 10 and
call this you know something like 2 to
four on a scale again of 1 to 10 so
there lots of different ways people
shake this up just to give you very
rough examples this is probably
something like 60 to 65% of your heart
rate again some folks will define those
numbers a little bit differently um this
could be exercise you could do while
maintaining a conversational pace so
lots of different ways uh to go about it
um you could make an argument for many
of them being better than others but
this is just getting you the basic idea
of lower intensity
exercises after that you move up to your
next zone or area again could be a
combination of Zone 2 or Zone 3 maybe
gear three on that system maybe others
call this a green color uh this is
probably something like an RP of five to
six maybe up to seven you're kind of in
this moderate uh intensity Zone heart
rates are going to range here between
that you know 65 all the way up to like
85% plus or minus you know something in
that neighborhood and then finally all
the way at the top you're now at 85%
Plus of your heart rate typically um
you're know into gear four uh in that
way of defining it and others would call
this red okay so you're really moving
really really hard you're definitely not
at conversation pace you're almost
surely not going to be able to breathe
through your nose Alone um you're going
to have to open up your mouth and you're
moving
here now depending on how trained you
are those three zones kind of blue green
and red might be enough if you are
highly trained um and you're comfortable
or even moderately trained you might add
fourth one on top of that I like to call
this one infrared and this is kind of
your 95% plus so there's a difference
and most folks would know this that
training at 80 to 85 or even 90% of your
heart rate is challenging but manageable
when you cross that threshold of 95 96
97 it is really honestly a different
thing 97% is not the same as 87% and so
I I kind of call that last 5% the
infrared zone so with all of these
things that are pros and cons okay the
global General benefit of the really
high intensity stuff is it creates a
tremendous amount of physiological
adaptation and a short amount of time
right so you're talking minutes to
seconds of work this could be things
like uh high-intensity intervals this
could be maximum allout efforts lots of
different stuff there typically 20
seconds to maybe you know like a couple
of minutes at most and then you're going
to repeat that effort time and and and
time in and time again the moderate
stuff is a little bit different it
requires uh not as much effort not as
much pain not as much suffering it's
going to be a little more time demanding
but it's not quite as as intimidating or
hard or mentally difficult to get into
for a lot of folks as the red stuff the
bottom stuff is the opposite also
effective U easier to do you you don't
necessarily have to have as diligent uh
of a warmup your injury risk is pretty
low but you're going to have to go for a
longer period of time I think you're
going to have a difficult time making a
cogent argument that you could stick in
any one of those zones for all of your
training and optimize your V2 I'm not
really sure I know of any research or
highle coaches that pick one zone and
stay in it entirely in fact I think
you're going to run into a lot of
problems with that and so most are going
to use a combination of these you know
three to four areas in various pieces
and ideally you're going to find you can
maximize the benefits of one of the
areas while minimizing the consequences
and that's how you blend your programed
together really quickly as an example
the downside of lower intensity stuff is
it doesn't create a lot of stimulus for
adaptation so it requires a long amount
of time okay the more time you spend in
a movement pattern the more likely you
are to have tissue injuries um you're
just simply creating more contact time
or more um overall exertion and the
biggest reason people don't exercise
number one by far is adherence and the
number one driver of adherence is time
okay so down sides there but if you go
to the other end and you go to that
infrared stuff well that's great the
total workout can be you know under 20
minutes but it really really Taps into
your recovery reserves it is way harder
to recover from 95% than it is even 90%
And so it's not a linear increase in
recovery with an increase in intensity
it's exponential and so you really have
to be concerned with dosing that stuff
too much because it it really takes away
your ability to recover which means it's
going to eliminate your other training
so that's really the game we're playing
with trying to improve our VO2 max we
also have specificity we need to pay
attention to so if you want to get
better at your V2 Max in a given
modality say this is on a rower then
you're going to get faster at that by
rowing okay we see that very clearly
there's excellent research on if you
take people and train them on a rower
and then have them do a VO2 max test on
a bike or running for that matter and
you compare that to their V2 Max on the
rower they're going to have greater
percentage increases in their V2 Max on
the rower than they will on the bike or
on the treadmill simply because they
became more efficient they became more
relaxed their motor patterns were better
etc etc so specificity is a way to get
an extra you know small but important
percentage increasing your V2 Max by
simply working on that modality so that
all being said let's go ahead and dive
into this sample program I've got
prepared for you now candidly it is a
little challenging to follow just
hearing my voice or watching this on the
video and so please go to the show notes
you're going to be able to download this
program there's a lot of graphics and
explanations and stuff that's going to
really help you use these things better
but it would be pretty challenging for
me to just explain this entire thing to
you step by step rep by rep for the
entire eight weeks um just verbally here
so you have more resources there if
you're having a hard time or maybe it's
not as crystal clear as you would like
it I'm going to do my best though to
walk you through it so that you can get
some usable information just simply
listening or watching the video just for
a little bit of context the program I'm
about to explain to you was developed to
improve V2 Max over an 8-week training
phase I'm going to get into the details
here in one second but it's important to
recognize this is probably best for
people who are of a fairly low training
age or physical fitness to up to kind of
moderate it can absolutely be used for
high level and Elite endurance athletes
but it's not optimized and designed for
that cause to give you an example the
program starts off pretty conservative
and works your way up if you're highly
trained you may want to be a little more
aggressive than that just a really easy
example if you've listened to the
previous episode we did on the heart and
cardiac tissue you may remember uh the
story of the Norwegian cyclist Oscar
senson his PR training program was
something like 75% of his time he worked
in the 60 to 82% heart rate Peak range
right this program is is not going to
get you that high that fast so Oscar
spent 75% of his time kind of 60 to
82% 20% of his time between 83 to
87% so again that's a differentiation
that we're not even going to make in
this program that kind of like mid upper
range and then only 5% of his time in
that 88% plus all right so um we're
going to have a similar theme and again
I think you will see most programs will
do that you're going to use a
combination of this low moderate and
high intensity stuff you're not going to
spend that much time at high intensity
you're going to dose it appropriately
and you'll probably spend the bulk of
your time in lower intensities but the
percentages here are really going to be
different than the percentages I'm about
to explain to you so that's the point I
really wanted to make um you may want to
start if you're moderately or just new
to training at a little bit lower
intensity and there's a lot of reasons
for that but we'll get into those at
another point so let's dive right into
it this program is called metamorphosis
and it was developed by Joel Jameson
Joel has been around for a very long
time a legend in the field of
conditioning if you will he's got a
fantastic book on conditioning you're
welcome to pick that up we'll have links
to all these things as well as Joel's
website he has excellent education and
courses and a whole bunch of other
training programs he is probably one of
the people most relevant in bringing HRV
which we've talked about in other
episodes to America and making it a big
part of it so a Monumental figure in um
the world of conditioning and endurance
has trained many professional athletes
and world champions along the way so I
know the program works I've used it
plenty of times and I've used a lot of
the concepts and I've red Joel's work
extensively for many years so I reached
out to him and I asked him if he was
okay with me sharing this entire program
with you and of course Joel's such a
great guy he said absolutely so this is
Joel Jameson's metamorphosis program and
his eight weeks designed to improve your
V2 Max it's going to start off with the
assumption that for the first month or
so we're going to build a foundation the
second month we're going to start
picking up the pace a little bit uh he's
got it developed and designed to be 5
days a week initially and then moving to
6 days a week after that of course if
that doesn't work for you feel free to
make the modifications that you need
whether you can do four days a week or
three or anything else so I'm going to
give you the specifics in details but
please I don't want you thinking that if
you can't follow this to a t that you
can't use a program at all think about
the concepts and adjust accordingly uh
for your circumstance so initially what
he's going to do for the first month is
say all right we're going to alternate
between what he calls kind of easy and
moderate right so day one is easy day
two is moderate day three is easy day
four is moderate then day five is easy
he's really again leaning heavily on
this lower intensity stuff trying to
work on cardiac output building stroke
volume building the heart's capacity
getting you more efficient developing
capillaries in your tissue and then
honestly getting you efficient in your
movement patterns you can use you know
again it's movement pattern agnostic so
you can cycle with this you can do
kettle bells with it you can do whatever
you would like to do um to continuously
move it's also designed and developed so
that people can pretty much jump right
into it and get going so again high
level thing here everything starts off
with a specific warmup you want to make
sure that your tissue is getting ready
to go so there's a sneaky important
thing that Joel does in this initial
part of the program you'll see him use a
lot of things like very low-level what
he calls aerobic petrics okay what that
means is you're not jumping up and down
on a box you could be doing something
like a rudimentary hop a Pogo hop some
very lowlevel um jump rope and he's not
doing that for the aerobic fitness
portion of it he's kind of building into
the warmup to save you time but he's
really working on what's called tissue
tolerance so if you want to be able to
put a lot of volume in say running your
ankles and foot need to become tolerant
to the load of your body weight smashing
into the ground the ground reaction
forces that happen every time you take a
stride or something like four to 5x your
own body weight and if you're going to
be doing that miles and miles and miles
every day or multiple days a week when
you previously have done none of it
that's going to build up on your tissue
and you're going to have lots of soft
tissue issues um potentially even joints
going Upstream to your knees and hip and
back and things like that that kind of
develop it's one of the reasons why I
say don't just jump in and start adding
miles so Joel is sneakily saying hey
we're going to have a warm-up here but
we're going to start building the
tolerance of these joints so that's a
component to all of it he'll also use a
lot of breath work to get going and to
get the nervous system activated or or
or ready to go prior to movement so
that's really consistent across all the
days I'd like to take a quick break and
thank our sponsors today's episode is
brought to you by eight sleep eight
sleep makes Smart mattress covers with
cooling heating sleep tracking and more
I've had one for years and it is
glorious I even put one on the bed in my
guest bedroom because as you'll hear me
talk about endlessly here on the perform
podcast there really is nothing you can
do that makes a larger impact on your
health and performance than getting
tremendous sleep the eight sleep is a
GameChanger because I run hot or as my
wife calls it I'm a furnace and that's
particularly driven by the fact that I
often have to do my exercise training in
the evenings which is honestly not
always great for sleep but this is also
the case of many of the athletes that I
work with who don't have a choice when
they compete and so being able to cool
down immediately in bed does wonders for
both sleep latency and Sleep Quality
eight sleep recently launched their
newest generation of the Pod cover the
Pod 4 ultra the Pod 4 ultra has two
times more cooling power yet is
virtually silent and even has snoring
detection that will automatically lift
your head in a few degrees to improve
the air flow and stop you from snoring
go to eights sleep.com perform to save
$350 off their pod 4 ultra eight sleep
currently ships to the USA Canada UK and
select countries in the EU and
Australia again that's 8sleep.com
/ perform today's episode is also
brought to you by momentus momentus
makes highquality nutritional and
dietary supplements I was deeply
skeptical of them as I am all supplement
companies given what I know about the
industry the low quality contamination
mislabeling and other issues plaguing
many companies in this space however I
was so impressed by what they're doing
and plan to do in the future that I
decided to not only bring them on as a
sponsor to the podcast but to formally
partner with them as well every single
one of their products is thirdparty
tested and 100% of their product line is
NSF or informed Sports certified giving
you peace of mind that you're getting
exactly what they say you are they're
also trusted and used by the best
meaning over 175 professional sporting
organizations that includes 28 major
league baseball teams 31 of 32 NFL teams
15 NBA 93 NCAA 7 MLS and three Olympic
teams I think you get the point no
supplement is mandatory even the
foundational ones or their grass-fed
whey protein isolate are never meant to
replace or be used instead of high
quality food however they do have a
strong base of scientific support and
give you more options to hit your macro
and micronutrient targets for example I
personally found that the recovery
powder is fantastic for getting protein
carbohydrates magnesium and some
glutamine in without needing to give my
coaching clients a ton of directions or
several supplements to carry around if
you'd like to give it a try go to
liv.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's liv.com perform to
get 20% off your order so from a big
picture perspective here's how the weeks
line up you're going to start off with
an easier day and then the second day is
going to be a moderate day and then
you're going to flip flop so day one is
easy day two is moderate easy moderate
easy right as the weeks go on you're
going to slowly start to build time and
a little bit of intensity within each
one so say on the easy day day one of
week one you'll have a 15 to 20 minute
workout then maybe the week two that
moves up to 22 minutes week three that
moves up to 24 minutes maybe you're
going to do on your moderate day a tempo
run with 10 rounds and then maybe by
week two you've gone up to 12 rounds so
very small increases as time goes on
once you get to week five there'll be a
different insert where we'll actually
have our hard day or a red day built in
there but overall you're seeing that the
progression is very slow and
conservative and that's how we can make
sure we're still challenging adaptations
while minimizing our risk of injury and
overuse so what I'd like to do is walk
you through a couple of the days I'll
start off with week one just to give you
a sample every day in the week is going
to have the same Three core components
you'll start off with a highquality
warm-up you'll do some sort of
conditioning and then some sort of
strength piece I'm going to go through a
couple of sample days to help you
understand but please check out the show
notes for the full program as that will
be a little bit easier for you to digest
so again just to keep this big picture
the warm-ups are going to be the same on
the easy days and then the same on the
moderate days for the conditioning piece
the easy days are going to be more
steady state lower intensity and the
moderate days are be going to be what we
call Tempo stuff I'll explain all this
to you in give you samples in just one
second for the strength component the
easy days are going to be split up so
that day one you'll do some sort of
upper body press and pull day two you'll
do some sort of lower body press and
Pull and then day three will be more
hinging and then a combination of upper
press and pull for your two moderate
days so days two and four your strength
work is going to be more core and
accessory based okay so that's the big
structure of how the week is laid out
let me walk you through a couple of days
here in detail so you can start seeing
what this stuff actually looks like so
let's go over day one of week one
remember there's three components to
every single day warm up
endurance and then strength now since
this is an endurance-based program you
notice we're doing the strength work
after the endurance if this was a
program designed to optimize strength or
muscle growth you might see the inverse
order but it's not because we keep the
thing that we are the have the most
priority on our biggest goal first right
so in this case the strength training is
really there just to supplement and keep
you healthy conditioning is the goal so
that's why we're going to do it first so
going through this very first day of
warm-up we'll start off with 5 minutes
of low intensity aerobic movement so you
can do whatever you like here jog
whatever you want here and then there's
three specific warm-up activities the
first one are ankle rolls so you're
going to do two or three sets of 8 to 10
most likely here we're doing this
because we're assuming people are going
to run and we're going to want to make
sure that those joints are warmed up and
activated so that we can move well and
not put ourselves into bad positions the
second exercise is going to be
windshield wipers um this is Imagine
standing and Swinging your feet out in
front of you left to right if you will
um warming up your adductors and um your
hips and low back and things like that
again two to three sets here of 8 to 10
repetitions and then finally a goblet
squat so this is now full range of
motion of our hips knee and Ankle I'm
holding a kettle bell in front of you in
front of your chest you just squatting
up and down for the same thing in total
here we've invested maybe five minutes
we've gone through a full range of
motion in most of our joints and we
should be activated and ready to go the
working conditioning sets here um are
going to start off with with calls
aerobic pentrix now this is very
important here because we're trying to
develop tissue tolerance right so this
is very lowlevel easy jumps we're not
jumping up and down on a box um we're
doing Pogo hops we're doing rudimentary
hops maybe some jump rope some very
light activities for two to three
minutes this is not going to be building
much conditioning in our cardiovascular
system that's not the point it's really
to give the joints in this case the
ankles the ability to start learning how
to develop tolerance to load over time
remember earlier when I talked about one
major mistake folks make is they just
start to hop into volume specifically
with running you want to give your
tissue the ability to get ready for that
you know you've probably heard and seen
and been aware of the Achilles snapping
epidemic that's happening right now a
lot of reasons that that's actually
going on but one way to make sure you
hedge your bets against that is just to
make sure your Achilles is being loaded
often so spending two to three minutes
hopping up and down prior to activity is
a pretty good way to build long-term
resilience throughout that joint so
that's in large part what that stuff is
in there for so then really we get into
our work and this particular stuff this
is going to be steady state lower
intensity stuff you're probably looking
at 70% maybe less probably less of
whatever exercise you would like again
if you are exercise specific you want to
get better at cycling get on a bike uh
push a sled go up a hill it doesn't
really matter as long as you're moving
consistently at this intensity and
you're going to do this for simply 15 to
20 minutes typically we're looking at
heart rates you know 120 beats per
minute or lower maybe a little bit
higher for some folks maybe a little bit
less but it is lower intensity stuff me
personally I'm going to be doing this
and recommending this entirely nasal
only breathing this is going to also
then help you work on your respiratory
muscle control breathing mechanics as
well as it kind of de facto keeps you at
a little bit of a lower intensity for
most of us from there you'd finish that
and go into your strength work so again
if you're counting here we've got a 5
minute warmup we've are now at most 20
22 to 23 minutes in uh to our
conditioning so we're you know under 30
minutes total investment at this point
and then from there that strength piece
is going to be remember it's going to be
upper body press pull what's that mean
often times and I like to program this
way as well rather than picking a
specific exercise then you just program
Concepts so upper body press this could
be a bench press this could be a push-up
this could be any number of things if I
know a lot about you and I'm privately
coaching you we're absolutely going to
select exercises with lot of intent but
if we're just giving Global
recommendations then an upper body you
know quote unquote press and pull is
great in this example a barbell bench
press um for two to three sets of 8 to
10 repetitions remember we're not trying
to drive hypertrophy or strength here
we're trying to just keep the joints
healthy develop a little bit of
mitochondria start getting blood flow
and getting the tissue able to handle
some tolerance of load eventually so
we're going to go you know reasonably
under control in terms of our tempo
maybe 4 seconds up 4 seconds down and
then rest you know 60 seconds or so in
between repetitions so maybe you would
pair that upper body pressing movement
with a pull in this case say a lat pull
down or a bent row same repetitions same
tempo same sets so those would be your
two exercises you pair there um if you
wanted to do those by themsel or you
wanted to suet them meaning you would
say do one set of bench press and then
one set of lap pull that would save you
some time there and you could absolutely
do that no problem second two exercises
then one of them is going to be a
rotational movement so this is a a cable
rotation or 9090 trunk rotation
something where we're moving in that you
know rotational field same thing 8 to 10
reps or so we're not trying to maximize
strength we're trying to just get a good
feel here and move on to the next one
and then finally um again an additional
repetition method here for you know
pushing and pressing maybe something
like a push-up where you do one sets for
as many reps as possible that entire
thing those four exercises you again
should not take you more than 10 or or
so minutes and so really we're out of
the gym in under 45 minutes which is not
that bad ideally before leaving you
would finish with some sort of aerobic
cool down and then really really ideally
and we've I've talked about this plenty
of times in my guest series with Dr
Andrew huberman on the huberman Lab
podcast and many other places but doing
some sort of down regulation breathing a
box breathing maybe a 4 second inhale 4
second hold 4 second exhale and a 4
second hold or really just any extended
exhale hold would be fine as well but
investing you know 3 to 6 minutes in
that before you walk out the gym would
be again the ideal scenario so that
would be day one of week one moving on
to day two your more moderate day since
we want a little bit higher intensity
here but remember we're still not in red
this is moderate at most we're going to
use something more like tempos rather
than steady state here's what I mean
when I say Tempo various coaches Define
this differently so in this particular
protocol what he's referring to is still
something that is you know easy this is
an RP of five or six maybe a heart rate
of 70% something like that maybe a
little bit lower but instead of just
saying hey go jog for 20 minutes
straight we're going to play with
intensity variations a little bit you
may also know this as flick training
that's an old Swedish term that's been
around since 1930s I think in fact I
think flick stands for like fast play or
something it's effectively saying all
we're going to pick a time let's just
say 20 minutes to make it easy and we're
going to continuously move for 20
minutes this this is not interval
training you're not resting you're not
recovering um you're in terms of like
taking time off you're going to
continually move the whole time but
you're going to play with intensities
throughout that duration so we're going
to go 20 minutes and instead of going uh
one pace it it actually kind of think
about this like anytime you've gone into
a hotel and you've hopped on an
elliptical or something like that and
they have those various workouts you can
play with and you pick the ones that's
kind of like the Rolling Hills so you're
going to do 20 minutes you're going to
kind of go up and down on intensities
but you're never going to go totally off
that's kind of what a fart lick is all
right again very different than a
high-intensity interval training where
you're going to go say 30 seconds or 90
seconds as hard as you can then you're
going to rest entirely or walk you're
going to maybe like active rest but
you're basically you know at zero and
then you're going to repeat that high
intensity intervals farli is not that it
is continuous movement but a rolling
intensity Tempo training is is kind of
like that as well at least according to
Joel here so in this example he's going
to say do something like 10 10 to 15 20
seconds of higher intensity this is not
high intensity just higher we're still
at an RP of five or six so we're going
to pick it up a little bit maybe we
shifted into gear two um nasal breathing
as fast as we can or as much as we need
to but it's not even close to 85% of our
heart rate we're not way up there it's
just a little bit higher we'll do that
for 10 15 maybe 20 seconds and then
we're going to back off and go kind of
all the way down to active movement the
lower intensity still moving for 60
seconds and so what again we really
working on here is not just jogging
straight or swimming straight it is kind
of moving up and down the intensity this
is a little bit different than steady
state that's why he differentiates the
two um we're going to be asking for
different physiological demands we're
going to go up we're going to come down
and we're going to build up a little bit
of waste and then recover build up a
little bit of waste and then recover uh
we're going to get to a touch higher
intensity and start dosing that in small
portions but not jumping all the way up
to really Max intent or Max effort types
of things so when we say Tempo that's
really what we're talking about so in
this particular day you'll do somewhere
between 8 to 10 repetitions of a Tempo
which would be something like 10 to 15
seconds of higher intensity work again
not all the way up coupled with you know
45 to 60 seconds of lower intensity so
we're going to be continually moving for
something like 8 to 10 minutes but we're
just going to kind of play and roll with
the intensity a little bit in terms of
heart rate zones or perceived exertion
for those 10 to 15 seconds of additional
work you're probably looking at 70%
heart rate maybe an RP of 5 to six so
again it's just a little bit higher but
it's still a moderate intensity at best
protocol our strength work for that day
is going to be core and accessory so
this could be something as simple as
some front and side planks for however
long you can hold them maybe two to
three rounds each of those and that'll
be a wrap and again as always ideally
some sort of down regulation breath work
before we walk out of the gym in this
example Joel likes to use what's called
be breathing
you can imagine a bear in the wilderness
kind of doing
the kind of thing so bear breathing is
like a 3se second inhale 3se second
exhale but you really want to put
yourself in that super
downregulated mentality that's really
the point of be breathing moving on then
to day three it's going to be similar to
day one still an easy day but just as
some sample here instead of doing our
conditioning for 15 to 20 minutes we
maybe Notch it up to 20 to 25 minutes
same basic idea could be the exact same
modality that you chose for day one our
strength work now is going to be a
little bit complimentary so instead of
doing our upper body press and pull it's
our lower body so now we're looking at
exercises like a barbell squat lunges
box step UPS cable exercises and things
like that so same concept we did before
but now we're just exchanging it for the
lower body moving on then to day four
you'll see that's actually very similar
to day two so it's a little bit more of
a moderate day with the tempo and the
same core and accessory exercises day
five then our final day is back and
basically a repeat of day one so that's
really as complicated as it needs to be
as I said we're going to progress all of
these things over time as the weeks go
on we start adding a small amount of
minutes we start adding a few more
repetitions per set not much though be
very conservative in your approach until
you get to week five where we finally
start adding in that red day let's Zoom
ahead now and see what would actually
look like when we integrate some of
these harder higher intensity days into
it so here we're looking at week five
same structure as before we've added an
additional day of training so we're
going easy day one moderate day two hard
day three moderate day four easy day
five and then moderate day six so we're
still doing two easy days we're doing
three moderate days and we've actually
sandwiched the hard one with two
moderate ones the day-to-day structure
is identical though still have the same
three components always a high quality
warm-up always some conditioning piece
and then always some sort of strength
piece it looks a little bit different
though now right now on the easy day day
one we're going to be using a
combination of our steady state and our
tempos so those are really in the same
day and then our strength work is still
that upper body press and pull day two
the moderate day we're going to be now
adding in a little bit more of repeat
works we'll talk about what those are in
a second and our core and accessories
for our strength piece our red day now
is still some steady state stuff but
we're going to go really into some
harder intervals after that and then
we'll finish with our strength work
which will be our lower body uh press
and polar Squat and lunch however you
like to think about it the fourth day so
again we're back to moderate now just
similar to day two here almost identical
approach and then the following day is
going to be an easier day where we're
really in a low intensity steady state
stuff followed by some hinging and our
upper body press and pull so we're
getting a combination there this allows
us in if you're paying attention we'll
have two days for strength work for
lower body two days for upper body and
two days for our core and accessory
that's why it's all buil together the
way it is there the sixth day which
again feels new here is really just
another moderate day where we're using
some tempos we're not doing the strength
piece at all there because we've already
gotten you know each area of our body
twice and a short work just an
additional kind of flush and Recovery uh
and get us moving final day so let's
break some of these days down
individually starting off with day one
going to feel really similar to what day
one of week one was remember this is an
easy day we're going to do you know that
20 to 25 minutes of our lower intensity
movement and then we're going to add in
some tempos on top of that so basically
you can say the tempos we talked about
earlier that used to be on day two is
now just added to day one so it's low 20
25 minutes of our steady state stuff
combined with 10 to 12 repetitions of
the temple work so we've added a lot of
work to this day the strength work is
very similar but now we're up to three
to four sets so we've added probably an
additional set for every exercise and
we've moved our repetition range up to
maybe sets of 10 to 12 right so small
subtle increases here they're going to
pay a lot of magnitude over time the
exercise selection can stay the same for
this entire day that you've been doing
the previous four weeks day two our
moderate day instead of using tempos
we're going to switch and use what are
called repeats okay so again these are
not high-intensity intervals it's not 30
seconds as hard as you can with rest
it's a little bit different Joel calls
them repeats so what you're looking at
here is RP of you know 6 to 7 or so um
heart rates probably closer to that 80
maybe 85% but not completely crazy we're
looking for bouts of 30 to 60 seconds of
elevated intensity this is certainly
Gear 2
in that system maybe even touching into
gear three though still probably gear
two so nasal only but as fast as you
need to ventilate and you're going to do
you know 10 or so repetitions of this so
30 to 60 seconds of harder work brought
back down still moving though 30 to 60
seconds elevated but what you're seeing
happen is rather than just jumping into
again Max effort high-intensity interval
thing we're slowly getting prepared for
that so let's get a little bit higher
intensity for a while come back down a
little bit higher intensity for a while
come back down first week
we kept this stuff at you know five to
six RP now we're five weeks in so now
that is up to 6 to 7 RP so we're just
gradually building this stuff over time
in this case over the course of a month
so all in there we're talking about 15
to 20 minutes total for our conditioning
of kind of repeating those 30 to 60c
moderate intensity intervals our
strength piece very similar the one we
talked about in week one but now we're
going to add Maybe more complicated core
exercises we'll add in some you know
trunk rotation stuff we'll do some more
advanced movements rather than just sort
of planking all the time and we're
probably looking at you know two to
three sets of 8 to 10 repetitions plus
or minus so again slowly building up
competency adding more difficult
movements um adding in whatever you have
available whether you have medicine
balls or bands or ropes or weights or
whatever you have access to and feel
comfortable and confident doing this
leaves us to day three which is our
first installment of a harder higher
intensity workout but please note we're
not trying to completely Max ourselves
out here we're just starting to get
closer to that top end intensity we
start off with our highquality warm-up
and then we move into 15 or 20 minutes
or so of a very low intensity steady
state so we don't want to leave that
component out we're continuing to get
those adaptation and and de facto it
works as a higher quality warmup and now
we're ready to go into what are called
Power intervals and so this is going to
look something like RP of s to8 I know
most of you are probably going to pick
eight you're you're going to get all the
way up there um heart rates are probably
you know 85% or so now uh in that ball
park you're definitely going to have to
be using your mouth to breathe at some
point you might be nasal in mouth out or
the opposite but we shouldn't be just
mouth only or at that maximum intensity
yet we're going to do 5 to 10 seconds of
work here and this work is going to be
high effort right we're really trying to
get after it um at the hardest way we
possi can now what keeps this from being
like a you know infrared level is the
fact that we're doing this for 5 to 10
seconds and so this is your ability to
repeat Peak power a bunch of different
times I love the style of training I've
done it for forever it's always blown my
mind why Nobody Does it it's so
effective so impactful um especially if
you're an athlete or you compete in
anything your ability to repeat power
outputs over time uh it's just so lost
people want to get to conditioning they
want to get to fatigue so they either
keep their rest is way too short or they
do way too many repetitions of this
where it ends up just being kind of like
moderate effort like kind of hard but
not truly hard um it's just a huge
mistake so make sure you're going really
hard in these short short short bouts
keep those bouts very short so you can
really get to Bak power recover and then
do it again that recovery is going to be
40 to 60 seconds so a really good
example that I use all the time is the
airault bike and we'll go 5 to 7 Seconds
as hard as we possibly can and then rest
for a minute that's what we're talking
about here maximal effort for 5 to 7
Seconds it feels like nothing resting
all the way upwards of a minute if you
want to you know press it a little bit
higher to like 10 seconds of work and 40
seconds of rest that's fine but we want
to be anywhere between like a 1 to 4 to
up to 1 to 12 work to rest ratio so what
that means is for every 1 second of work
we have up anywhere between five to 12
times the amount of rest so a 5-second
work out with 60 seconds of rest you can
do the math there on that ratio 10
seconds of work 40 seconds of rest
that's a one to four ratio right but we
want to go all the way up there one: one
like 30 seconds on 30 seconds off are
fine but they're just fundamentally
training something different than what
we're trying to get after here and that
is your again repeated Peak power so in
this first day of the truly High effort
stuff we're just going to repeat that
for 8 to 10 repetitions so again to
really be clear here say you do 5
Seconds of allout work on the assault
bike you rest for a minute you do 10
rounds of that and you're good as you
build up your abilities over time you
will increase that number and so instead
of 10 repetitions you'll go to 15
repetitions eventually or all the way up
to 20 or even more if you'd like you
could start extending the work time so
go from 5 Seconds to 10 seconds you
could start reducing the the rest so
going from 60 to 40 but please please
please please keep in mind simply
reducing rest and and making it feel
harder is not always making it better if
we're compromising our ability to
produce power in this case we've
undercut what we're
attempting value there but it's a
different thing right so just adding
weight just making things harder just
reducing rest is not necessarily always
the best approach for progression so you
may be thinking to yourself well that's
not a hard day well a couple things we
haven't done our strength work yet and
remember it's just our first touch at
this here right we're going to have more
stuff built in later so our strength
work in this day is just three exercises
in this case a squat a lunge and
something for our core you could do a
super set with all these if you'd like
and you're really going to be trying to
keep your resting lels fairly low 60
seconds at most three to four sets or an
8 to 12 repetitions or so per set and as
always always always we finish that up
with some sort of down regulation work
in this case probably worth it to do
some sort of phys physical unwinding so
some sort of stretching or Mobility that
could be combined with your breath work
and down regulation but you want to
bring the pieces back out that you've
sort of condensed with the higher
intensity work I also need to remind
some of you while you're just raring to
go here you had a moderate day before
that you're about to have another
moderate day right after this and so
hard is really the context of the entire
week we're working out six days that
week we're doing a decent amount of work
every single day this is going to
accumulate over time another another
major mistake that uh we've seen in in
the athletes we've worked with as well
as younger coaches that I've mentored is
really not appreciating what's going to
happen over the course of the week and
then over the course of those weeks
stacking up it's not necessarily just
about the individual workout it is
really the thought and progression over
the next week to months that matters and
so in this particular case we've added
an extra day we've added repetitions
we've added sets and now we're adding a
whole bunch of higher intensity stuff
that we haven't done yet this is a big
difference than week four and it's even
a big difference than week three and so
keep our eye on the prize of total
volume number we'll always stick with
for the most part is you don't want to
add more than about 10% volume or
intensity per week and so what that
really means is a couple of extra sets
or a couple of extra even repetitions on
every workout multiplied by five days
gets that number to 10% really really
really quickly right so your fatigue
over the week will start to build up
this may not seem like a lot of
high-intensity or nearly enough that you
want from some of you folks out there
but appreciate what's happening on the
other days of the week and so what you
don't want to do is train harder than
recommended on this day and have that
compromise the next moderate day's
workout or even the one following that
so appreciate the process there is
extensive science behind this and a lot
of coaching experience um the program
will work you will get enough
high-intensity stuff in there and we'll
get you everything that you want moving
us all the way to the end week8 is the
hardest in terms of both duration and
intensity so it's the most volume you'll
do at the highest heart rate or effort
however you're monitoring it and that's
the same structure as we just walked
through in weeks five but just slightly
more advanced and that's because on the
fifth day which is traditionally an easy
day you're going to actually do your
test so how do we know if your program
worked well in this case if you have
access to a metabolic cart and you've
done a vehic to Max tests before and you
want to test it after this would be a
day to do it if not you can simply do
any number of sub maximum tests the
great one one we talk about all the time
is a Cooper's 12-minute test so you're
effectively going to take 12 minutes on
a track run as far as you possibly can
in that 12 minutes and then you're going
to enter that distance in and that will
give you a prediction of your VO2 maxus
it's an easy way uh to get a pretty good
scientifically validated estimate of
your vi2 max so if you wanted to do a
little bit of pre- and post testing uh
you could actually do it that way and
and validate whether or not the program
worked for you so once again if you want
more information about this program you
can check out the show notes as well as
Joel's website it's called 8weeks
out.com and they've got a bunch of
different programs on there for all
kinds of different scenarios and outcome
so check out those resources for more
information I'd like to take a quick
break and thank our sponsors today's
episode is brought to you by ag1 ag1 is
a foundational nutrition greens
supplement and what's that mean it means
that ag1 provides a comprehensive
variety of vitamins minerals probiotics
prebiotics and adaptogens in an easy to
drink greens powder getting your
nutritional right is hard for many
people I certainly know that I have
clients who really struggle for whatever
reason to get the proper nutrients from
whole food sources now ag1 is not a
replacement for eating high quality
Whole Foods but it is a great
foundational supplement for filling in
the gaps or needed I've also personally
found that with many of my clients ag1
helps move them just in the right
direction for eating more high quality
foods because it helps them with
Cravings digestion and many other
benefits I especially personally like
taking ag1 when I'm on vacation or
traveling because it helps me just sort
of stay on track with my nutrition I
know that missing a few days of getting
the proper vitamins and minerals and
other micronutrients is not a big deal
at all that's not really how those
things work but for me again I just like
knowing that I'm kind of staying
somewhat on track when I'm definitely
not making the best nutrition and food
choices of my life if you'd like to try
ag1 you can go to drink a1.com perform
to receive five free travel packs plus a
year supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 again
that's drink a1.com perform to receive
five free travel packs plus a year
supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 so let's
move on and talk about our training for
our first marathon program now a little
bit of a backstory here this is called
faster in 50 because it was designed to
get you to a marathon in 50 days days
really important though and actually you
could say the same for the previous
program just because that was 8 weeks
long and this one's 50 days long they
don't necessarily have to be that there
are two big components of faster and 50
which we'll talk about in a second and
they're broken up as phase one is 25
days and phase two is 25 days 50 in
total but they could be much longer so
if you're not in the same position that
this individual was in uh for 25 days
and you need longer for that
foundational piece make that
foundational piece 50 days make it 150
days make the second piece longer it's
absolutely fine all these programs are
meant to get to a certain place so if
you're not there as fast as this
individual was or you're starting off in
a different spot which almost surely is
the case please want to make sure you
understand this does not have to be done
in just 50 days it also definitely does
not have to be done in 50 consecutive
days right so we can extend this thing
out um to be meeting you where you're at
and your needs for improving your
Marathon now as we take a quick step
back when we look at success in a
marathon there's three specific
components we just got done talking
about a program designed to improve your
V2 Max but that's only one of the three
major predictives of success in a
marathon the other two are your lactate
threshold and then your movement
efficiency okay now we also have to
think about whether you're trying to
maximize your performance in a marathon
or simply finish it those are also very
different goals right many of us in this
case this program was designed for
somebody running their very first
marathon ever it's just trying to
accomplish all 26.2 miles without having
to fail or stop or try again if you can
already do that and you're highly
successful say you're already running a
three-hour marathon and you're trying to
get a faster that really is a different
approach okay um so really want to just
walk you through this program of faster
and 50 again designed to help people go
from zero to their first ever marathon
in 50 days as we've done before you can
have direct access to this full program
there'll be links to this in our show
notes as well as the actual program and
you can go check it out faster and 50
was developed by two individuals Mark
Bell and Dan Garner and so the backstory
here is Mark Bell if you don't know him
is a lifelong powerlifter and
bodybuilder he has been training for
probably 30 years he's competed in
numerous powerlifting events and
competitions and bodybuilding events he
is outward about his long use of I
abolic steroids and many other agents
but really what's interesting about this
is you have an individual who's you know
probably 6 feet tall or so has weighed
certainly 300 lb or more and has spent
his lifetime either maximizing muscle
growth or strength anything in the realm
of conditioning was completely off the
table M Mark was very anti- running very
anti- conditioning for a long part and
if he did do it it was higher repetition
range lifting no running that I know of
really before he started this certainly
very minimal um conditioning at all and
so for whatever reason Mark decided he
wanted to take up running so he had done
this for a while I can't remember how
long maybe uh four or five months or
something like that and then decided
because he's Mark Bell that he wanted to
go from just running to running a
marathon and that first marathon needed
to be Boston and so this is the actual
program Mark used to run his first ever
Marathon at probably 230 lbs so what he
did is realized he couldn't handle that
himself so he reached out out to a guy
named Dan Garner who's a human
performance expert and he asked him to
build him a comprehensive program to run
his first ever Marathon this included
his nutrition his supplementation his
recovery sleep lifting running and all
of that it's all in that free program
I'm not going to go into the details of
all the supplements and nutrition and
everything else right now so we're just
going to focus on what the training
program looked like for those final 50
days again do want to reiterate he
didn't start at zero here he was already
running for a while he was somewhat fit
this is kind of like their last final
push and so if you're literally starting
from nothing you may want to take this
first phase which for Mark was only 25
days and that itself might need to be 50
days or 60 days or even 150 days for you
before you're ready to move on to the
second phase so caveat side let's jump
into what faster and 50 looks like the
first thing to pay attention to here is
just like in the previous program there
is a dedicated and specific warmup for
each day so in this case there's an
upper body lift
a lower body lift and then of course
you're running and so you can see the
full details in the program if you
choose to check that out but just really
quickly the upper body warmup is going
to be things like uh cat camel exercises
bird dogs push-ups jumping jacks uh yws
and things like that same idea usually
one to three sets 8 to 10 repetitions
per exercise so a full body full joint
upper body dedicated warm-up for the
lower body it's a similar approach but
now you're talking about about things
like mountain climbers and fire hydrant
and walking lunges and single leg hip
thrusts and things like that same kind
of repetition ideas um really what we're
getting at is a combination of what's
called unilateral so this is one of the
two joints moving while the other one
rests as well as bilateral so both
moving at the same time easy example of
this a goblet squat is bilateral both
legs where a step up is unilateral so
somewhere in your warmup you want a
combination of these things and you want
pressing and pulling and you can want to
ask the joint to kind of do everything
that it's supposed to do in its normal
range of the motion the running warmup
is going to be a combination of very low
intensity aerobic exercise so skipping
jogging cycling stuff like that maybe
some full body goblet squats or coak
squats some skips and hops some some
low-level Plyometrics and really other
things that you would consider to just
be General basic calisthetics as I
mentioned the program is built into two
unique phases the very first one is
really meant to build your foundation
it's it's the tissue tolerance we talked
about earlier it's General conditioning
it's work capacity and it's getting you
physically prepared to handle the
training necessary to run the marathon
the second phase is really specific
Marathon prep so you're going to start
getting understanding of your race Pace
how do you know if you're going too fast
or too slow how is that stuff feeling
you're going to work on your fueling and
Recovery what should you be eating or
drinking at what time what upsets your
stomach what makes you feel great and
all those other things that go into
actually running a marathon that are not
just your physical training program so
those other components often get
forgotten and left about in fact I'll
never forget as a doctoral student I I
was sitting in my cubicle and another
one of the students was getting ready
for I think it was his first marathon
actually if not his first it was second
or something like that and he was
talking about and strategizing over what
he was going to use for his fuel during
the race and he came up with this plan
and all these you know young scientists
are talking about the research and what
should be taken and what amounts and all
that stuff and I was like oh that's
really cool and he was pretty close I
think he was maybe a month out and I
asked I'm like well awesome what are you
doing training right now and he looked
at me blankly he's like wow I just run I
was like wait wait so like you're going
to spend all this time developing an
optimal training and fueling strategy
but you're not even going to practice it
and just like the look on his face as he
stared and realized like oh my gosh like
how did I forget that part I'll never
forget it was quite amusing so the point
I'm getting at here is you want to
absolutely try every component uh that
you're going to use your warmup your
cool down all this stuff should be tried
prior to the competition and so this
last month is really about practicing
the race in all of its components so
what's the structure look like of these
different phases let's start off with
phase one that Foundation it's broken up
into seven days seventh day by the way
is optional e either recovery run or
totally off so very similar to the VO2
max program day one is going to be an
upper body lift combined with interval
running and this is also where
definitions matter they don't
necessarily Define intervals and Tempo
and things like that the same as the
previous one so I'll I'll clarify what
they mean by that so again day one is an
upper body lift combined with an
interval training day two is a lower
body lift plus Temple running and then
day three is more that classic flick
running style day four is the second
upper body lift so very similar two days
for upper body two days for lower body
little bit of a different workout out
here so upper body the second one as
well as a recovery run day five is lower
body lift as well as a cross trainining
and I'll explain what that is and then
day six is a long slow run now remember
this is designed specifically for a
marathon it's not for v2 Max and so
you'll see some subtle differences there
that matter but really conceptually
they're doing the same thing a little
bit of lifting running in different
zones some higher intensity stuff some
lower intensity stuff in this case the
goal is to run for 26 straight miles so
you have to practice running for longer
distances at some point that's not a
requirement though it can work but it's
not a requirement to improving your V2
Max so slight differences here because
we're actually after a different Target
but a lot of the same Concepts the
second phase is a little bit different
so day one is now a total body lift plus
intervals day two is a longer fart lick
strategy day three a total body lift
again plus a Temple Run day four is a
shorter higher intensity fart lick and
then day five and six are longer slower
runs and then finally again day seven is
off now you notice they've cut the
lifting in half and they've extended the
long runs they've doubled those in fact
and they've actually doubled the farlex
and this makes a ton of sense you're
trying to run a marathon lifting is
important but running is more important
and so they' they've doubled down on
that and we've said we instead of having
upper body days and lower body days will
just combine to have total body days so
each muscle is still getting two per
week but we've deemphasized that because
we need to over uh again continue to
emphasize actual running we need to
practice running long distances slow and
we need to practice running distances
fast both of those are going to be
required to successfully complete your
Marathon cool now you got the big
picture let's go in and cover a couple
of specific samples again you're welcome
to download the entire program
completely free so I can't go through
all of it but I I will give you some
examples uh to make sure these things
make sense and clarify some of the
terminology so let's just go into day
one of that first phase remember this is
an upper body lift very similar rather
than programming the specific exercise
it's done by concept and so you're going
to have a horizontal press you're going
to have a unilateral horizontal press on
top of that and so this would be
something like a bench press with a then
single armed dumbbell press something
like that uh you're talking three sets
or so for five repetitions plus or minus
we're trying to go a little bit heavy uh
in this case not all the way though what
we're trying to work on is strength so
we need that we're going to get
endurance and muscular endurance long
duration endurance from our running and
so what we're trying to get with our
lifting is the stuff we can't get all
right so we're trying to get a little
bit more strength development here not
maximal strength we're not competing in
powerlifting or weightlifting but we are
trying to get closer to that end of the
spectrum so three sets of five here for
your horizontal press and three sets of
eight or so per side for your L
unilateral press you then follow that up
with a Vertical Press so something
overhead and then basically do the same
thing for the pulling so you do your
three pressing exercises horizontal
bilateral horizontal unilateral and then
vertical and then you combine that with
horizontal pulling unilateral horizontal
pulling and then the same thing in this
case they chose a medial delt so same
basic idea here upper body is now taken
care of after this we're going to go
into our our running exercise now you
notice they've chosen to lift first and
then run after that but the upper body
lift is not going to interfere with our
running really whatsoever and so the
running here is going to be three one M
runs with a 3 minute walk in between
also keep in mind you're talking about
an individual here who's certainly over
230 PBS I don't remember exactly he was
but maybe a little bit more so they're
going to have to approach this running
and distance stuff a lot differently
than if somebody was 160 or 70 PBS
that's just a lot more mass on the
joints and so if you're wondering as
this program evolves why certain things
are done this way say you have more
experience with running or coaching um
this this is the large component of it
making sure more get to the race healthy
and then of course complete the 26 miles
but that's a little bit different from
somebody who's you know historically
been 270 to over 300 lbs for most of his
life even though he's lighter now we're
still a pretty large individual here and
a typically large for a marathon
so nonetheless the endurance training
like I said it is three one M runs with
a three minute rest in between so you
would run a mile rest for 3 minutes and
then repeat that so you're going to
accumulate three total miles of running
um you're not going to do these at Fast
Pace at all you're probably nasal
breathing or close um but you're not
walking either this is a fast Jog and
you want to think of this as more of
like seven to maybe eight out of 10 in
terms of perceived speed so you're
moving here you're going to be fatigued
you're not going to be having an easy
light jog here we're trying to
accumulate High work some rest and get a
lot of volume in without having to beat
up the joints too much so you'll do that
those three one mile repeats and then
you'll do the same thing but instead of
being a mile you'll do a half mile so
three half mile repeats with 90 seconds
of rest in between still same effort up
there so if we do that we've accumulated
4 and a half total miles of running
which is actually pretty good so you
think about this for somebody um at the
first phase here 4 and a half total
miles accumulated but you're able to do
that at a pretty high Pace um generate a
lot of endurance in a lot of different
areas while also getting some miles in
day two is the lower body lift combined
with what's called Tempo now in this
case again Tempo is means a different
thing than what we talked about earlier
the lower body lift follows a very
similar structure three sets of five for
the most part you're going to do some
unilateral stuff and some bilateral
stuff some sort of squat variations some
sort of lateral lunge or lateral
movement variations some sort of hinging
and some sort of carry and then this
case some sort of anterior rotation of
the core so your core tends to rotate
and you're going to stop that from
happening lots of different examples of
that and your endurance work is going to
be a 30 minute tempo run so this is
going to be like steady jog Pace if you
will I think seven out of 10 um and what
you're trying to kind of get used to is
is what that marathon pace is is
actually going to be um so if if you
know your half marathon time you can
actually use that pace for these temple
runs but you're you're kind of just
accumulating race Pace volume if you
come from an endurance racing background
this is probably what you what you
associate with temple runs it's kind of
like race Pace a lot of time um but for
a shorter duration so that would be our
endurance piece for day two day three is
that flick run I've already explained
what that means but as a reminder it's
kind of that cyclic variation of
intensities that are not true off period
so it's going to be 45 consecutive
minutes and within that you've got nine
opportunities to cycle up for one minute
but you can do those whenever you'd like
so it doesn't necessarily matter if you
go kind of 3 minutes at an easier pace
and then one minute higher and time it
out it doesn't really matter you can
kind of feel this out you just need to
accumulate nine of those one minute
bursts before that 45 minutes is
complete during those one minute bursts
you're going to go hard this is kind of
like nine out of 10 you want to push the
pace here and then you're going to slow
back down during that recovery it's not
walk
it's not uh off it is still back to kind
of your slow jog your slow movement but
you're going to cycle those things up
and down uh that kind of recovery Pace
think of that is like five or six out of
10 day four is another upper body lift
similar to the first lift as well as a
30 minute recovery run this is really as
low and slow as you need it to be you're
just really trying to build a little
more tissue tolerance here as well as
some general physiological recovery
almost always we're going to want this
to be nasal only to keep you you nice
and slow we just want to get out and
move a little bit day five is our second
lower body lift combined with a 30
minutes of what Dan calls cross training
this is really just active play it is
could be done on multiple different
things so a lot of times you'll do five
minutes on a rower five minutes on a
treadmill five minutes on a bike you may
do something like play basketball or do
light Jiu-Jitsu drilling or whatever is
the case you're not again really trying
to stimulate adaptation here it's most
used for recovery and pacing and blood
flow you want to accumulate 30 total
minutes but you just want to be moving
at a very light intensity ideally it's
not just running you're going to be
putting in a lot of miles uh on that
specific movement pattern so if you can
open up the system a little bit more and
choose some other movement patterns is
probably a good thing to do in this case
day six is when you do your long slow
run you want to keep these at an
intensity of something like six out of
10 on your rpu scale and you're going to
slowly increase the miles over time so
you get a sense you might start off with
like six miles week one and then week
two move up to 8 Miles and then a 10 and
then a 12 or something like that by week
four so pretty straightforward here
you're going to go out go easy but you
need to just accumulate the ability to
run for that many consecutive miles day
seven our final day is optional SL
recovery if you want to go do 20 or 30
minutes of very light movement you can
you're also welcome to skip that I would
though recommend as Dan does here to
pick at least what we typically call
recovery accelerators I'd like to have
at least two or three of these this
could be anything from a massage to
Thermal so cold or hot treatment um
breath work sessions um movement
acupuncture something like that that's
going to really aid in recovery so
typically we'll pick at least again two
to three things from that list could be
very short but that's going to get you
set up for the next day of work and
really the following week in general as
you cruise through weeks one to 4 you're
going to see slight increases of
intensity and variation throughout all
the days you can see all that detail in
the program but really as we get into
week five or our second phase things do
change I talked a little bit earlier
about how the structure changes in
general so you can refer back to that or
look at the PDF if you're actually
looking at it right now um so to walk
you through really quickly what we're
looking like here so now for example on
day one of our new phase our endurance
training instead of looking like those
three one M repeats like we had in our
first phase plus the half mile repeats
remember we totaled 4 and a half miles
there now our endurance training is
something like 10 3/4 of a mile repeats
with 3 minutes rest in between right so
we're doing these as fast as possible
but not all outpaced this is nine out of
10 and so we've done a similar structure
but we've really added it instead of
going a mile and a half a mile we're
really at 3/4 of a mile and we're doing
a lot of them 10 of them is going to
accumulate a lot of work day two's flick
run has gone from 45 5 minutes all the
way up to 90 minutes and so we've added
a bunch of more work there and so again
you can really see the concept as we're
just slowly building these things over
time we've got our lifts in there we've
got our Tempo runs those have now gone
up to 45 minutes where they were
previously 30 minutes and we're just
again slowly accumulating volume over
time we've got our now two additional
days so in this phase day five and day
six are for long runs day five for the
first week of this phase is going to be
at 8 Miles then the next week we'll
progress up to 10 miles and then really
we'll kind of back off from there and
keep it at that 8 mile range or so we're
really trying to move volume here but
this is not the biggest day because on
day six we're going to be at 14 miles
for week one 16 miles for week two 20
miles for week three and then really
week four will be all the way up to 24
miles this is basically Marathon
practice okay those additional 2.2 miles
really do matter on race day trust me
anyone who's done a marathon will tell
you yeah doesn't sound like a lot those
last 2.2 miles are a bunch so it's not a
full Marathon but we've walked oursel up
this hill slowly enough to where we
should be able to handle that you're
going to be tired and fatigued but it
shouldn't completely break you um smash
your toes or put you in really big
injury risk or anything like that from
running those 24 miles from here we've
gotten all the way up to our final week
and so let me walk you through what
those seven days look like or what we'll
call peak week with a little bit of a
taper and Marathon prep day one is going
to be be that phase two total body lift
plus a very short 15 minute or so
recovery run day two another total body
lift with a short recovery run and
really we're not trying to proess
adaptation here we're just trying to
keep the system activated keep blood
flowing keep feeling really good and
start tapering and optimizing for
performance day three is an easy F mile
run um start out at a really easy Pace
here and then really only target your
race pace for the final 2 miles so you
just want to um kind of kind of feel it
right this is like a golfer who goes out
and just hits a couple of shots to
remember what those feel like but you're
not going to spend hours on the Range
really getting all the way up to maximum
speed so five miles in total you're kind
of just moving and cruising for the
first three feel out that race pace for
two miles and then shut her down day
four isn't completely off as well as
maybe a couple of those recovery
strategies as day five is these often
tend to be travel days too if you're
going to the event and get hotel or
something like that but you're really
now just maximizing
recovery day six or what it was actually
the day before the marathon you might
want to do like a 15-minute recovery run
get loose stretch out a little bit but
not excessively and then really really
recover because day seven you wake up
and you run your first ever Marathon as
I said this was the actual program Mark
used he did run the Boston Marathon he
did complete it in a time of six hours
and according to mark it took him six
hours to run the marathon and only 6
hours to recover which is sort of funny
but if you've actually ever run a
marathon you realize that's actually
really fast he actually told me
personally the next day he felt great
wasn't even sore uh and then ran the
next day which is also very weird and so
6 hours is not a fast time for a
marathon in fact it's like close to the
range where they'll cut you off and say
you can't go anymore but that wasn't the
point here he's not trying to run the
fastest marathon he could he just wanted
to run one and complete it and so I
think the program
is clearly a success if that's something
you're interested in doing just wanting
to accomplish a task like that I have no
doubts that the program would work for
you as well it's also worth highlighting
that while Mark ran the marathon at what
some might call a little bit of a slower
Pace I think it came out to be about a
14-minute mile or so that doesn't mean
you can't use this exact program and run
as fast as you want for the most part
what's actually going to determine your
time is going to come down to in large
part what Paces you're able to manage
across this entire program particularly
the pace you can handle during your
Tempo runs so while Mark used it to run
his first ever marathon and run at a
pace that was effective and economical
for him you can use this to run as fast
or slow as you'd like to wrap up I know
we covered a lot of ground here so
please do check out these programs in
the show notes if you want to see them
or actually follow them yourself please
also check out the people Dan Garner
Mark Bell and Joel Jameson who are kind
enough to let me share with the world
for free their full training programs so
check out their material as well I also
wanted to mention a resource I have
found particularly helpful over my
career is a book called unbreakable
Runner it is a phenomenal place to learn
more about training specifically for
running andurs without getting hurt I
hope you enjoyed this episode it's a
little bit different than normal and
something we're going to consider doing
more often if this is something that you
appreciate so please do let us know if
this is something You' like us to try
again thank you for joining for today's
episode our goal is to share exciting
scientific Insight that helps you
perform at your absolute best if the
show resonates with you and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave up to a
five-star review given that we're a new
podcast subscribing and leaving a review
really does help us a lot second please
check out our sponsors the show would
not exist without them and they really
are exceptional products and services
and then finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comment section on YouTube
I really do try to read these and see
what you have to say I use my Instagram
and Twitter also exclusively for
scientific communication so those are
great places to follow along for more
learning my handle is Dr Andy Galpin on
both platforms thank you for listening
and never forget in the famous words of
Bill Bowerman if you have a body you're
an athlete